Inventory of the Iranian Political Opposition Literature collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Iranian Political Opposition Literature collection
1961-2003
2006C15
Hoover Institution Archives
86 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (36.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
This collection includes printed matter published by Iranian political opposition groups in exile relating to the social, political, and economic conditions in Iran, Kurdistan, and among Iranian students abroad from just before the Iranian revolution to the years following the Iran-Iraq war, represented in the form of monographs, booklets, pamphlets, journals, newsletters, and other circulars.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Hamid Shawkat collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Iranian subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Iran Freedom Foundation records, Hoover Institution Archives
James F. Hitselberger collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Sazman-i Mujahidin-i Khalq issuances, Hoover Instituion Archives
Historical Note
Beginning in 1983, Edward A. Jajko, at the time the former Middle East curator of the Hoover Institution Archives, set about the task of "gathering materials issued by or related to individuls and groups classifiable as belonging to an Iranian opposition, whether anti-Shah, anti-Khomeini, or otherwise in some form of political opposition" (Jajko, 1986). Between 1983 and 2006, the archives accumulated a wide variety of printed resources from the Hoover Library, University of Texas Library, and individual private donors. An initial inventory of the Middle East Collection in the Library and Archives was written and published by Jajko in 1986. The following finding aid reflects the collection as whole and does not make distinctions between the original accession and later additions.
Source: Jajko, E.A. (1986). Iranian Opposition Literature in the Middle East Collection of the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace. Updated January 5, 1987.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection contains printed matter published by Iranian political opposition groups in exile relating to the social, political, and economic conditions in Iran, Kurdistan, and among Iranian students abroad from just before the Iranian revolution to the years following the Iran-Iraq war, represented in the form of monographs, booklets, pamphlets, journals, newsletters, and other circulars.
Under the Pahlavi dynasty, followed quickly by the Islamic regime, Iranian dissidents faced the hurdles of exile, censorship, torture, imprisonment, and even death for holding political convictions contrary to the party in power. Unable to organize within Iran's borders for fear of retribution, Iranian political opposition groups (hereafter referred to as the IPO) of all persuasions rebanded abroad between the 1960s and 1970s.
From a broad view, the beliefs of the IPO can be classified as Monarchist, Marxist, Islamist, or Democratic (Metz, 1987). From each of these ideologies sprung a number of organizations motivated by a strong theoretical conviction, be it anti-capitalist, anti-socialist, or even more simply, anti-torture. As with all modern political struggles, the members of each organization actively engaged in the spread of propaganda and distributed printed materials locally and internationally.
Although the major IPO groups hold distinctive ideologies, the contents of the collection highlight some of the connective strains of thought and experience that unite these groups. For example, the 1971 raid of police headquarters in Siyahkal (a small town in the Gilan province of Iran) by members of the People's Sacrifice Guerrillas of Iran marked a change in the narrative of the IPO movement, inspiring the more violent factions of each group away from peaceful resistance and toward armed struggle. This event sparked Persian translations of works by Che Guevara and Leon Trotsky, as well as original writings by IPO "martyrs" A.P. Pouyan, Bijan Jazani, and Khosrow Golsorkhi, which are all included in the collection.
Besides highlighting the ideologies of each group, materials in the collection also describe how IPO groups were able to train their followers and operate covertly. Some of these unique materials include an instructional manual for cryptic writing (ramz nivisī), a first aid manual for guerrilla fighters, an assortment of lyrical ballads, and a memorial calendar marking important dates and events.
Other topics covered include political prisoners; human rights; Kurdish independence; martyrs and martyrdom; Iran-Iraq relations; Iranian students in the United States and Europe; the Iran hostage crisis; Iranian nationalism; and the spread of Marxist-Leninist thought in Iran.
The order in which each series appears reflects the original order of the collection as defined by Edward Jajko. Each series is comprised of printed matter published by a particular Iranian political opposition group or by its supporters. Because the materials are described for the most part at item level, the titles are grouped into subseries by physical format, for example as serials or monographs, then in alphabetical order by title with serial issues listed in chronological order. Printed matter that is not related to any specific political opposition is arranged at the end of the collection in the Other Printed Matter series.
In describing this collection, the solar Hijri calendar is used to more accurately reflect the original language of the materials, alongside the Gregorian calendar date.
Source: Metz, H.C. ed. (1987). Iran: A Country Study. Washington: GPO for the Library of Congress. Accessed from http://countrystudies.us/iran/
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Communism--Iran.; Iran--Politics and government--1941-1979.; Iran--Politics and government--1979-1997.; Political prisoners--Abuse of--Iran.; Sāzmān-i Chirīk'hā-yi Fadā'ī-i Khalq-i Irān.; Sāzmān-i Mujāhidīn-i Khalq (Iran).
Collection Contents
- Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān, 1967-1993; 1-12 (Box 1-12)
  Includes printed matter published by the Tudeh Party of Iran and its supporters.
  Arranged in three groups by physical format: Serials, Monographs, booklets, and pamphlets, and Administrative materials
  - Serials (Folder 1-6)
    - Ārmān, neshrī-yi dabīrkhāneh-yi khārijī-yi Sāzmān-i Javānān va Dānishjuyān-i Dimukrat-i Īrān, journals, 1354-1357 (1975-1978) (Folder 1: 1-4)
      - Sāl-i 1-2, shumārah-i 1, 10-12, 1354 Farvardin (1975 March-1977 March) (Folder 1: 1)
      - Sāl-i 3, shumārah-i 1-12, 1356 Farvardin-Esfand (1977 April-1978 March) (Folder 1: 2-3)
      - Sāl-i 4, shumārah-i 1-4, 1357 Farvardin-Tir (1978 April-July) (Folder 1: 4)
    - Azerbaijān, neshrī-yi sīyāsī va t'urik-i kumiteh-yi markazī farqī dimukrat Azerbaijān sāzmān-i Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān dar Azerbāijan, (Stockholm: Hizb-i Tudah), journal, 1367 (1988) (Folder 1: 5)
    - Bulitan-i bahs'hā-yi nazarī-sīyāsī (dawruni), shumārah-i 4-6, bulletin, 1366 Mordād (1987 July) (Folder 1: 6)
    - "Bulitan-i dafā'i khabarī," Kumiteh-yi Hamahangī-yi Īrān Dimukrat, shumārah 3, newsletter, 1362 Mehr (1983 September) (Folder 1: 7)
    - Donyā, incomplete issues, journals, 1348-1354 (1969-1975), undated (Folder 1: 8)
      Missing pages
    - "Information Bulletin: Review of the Foreign Bureau of ODYSI," no.5, 1978 July (Folder 1: 9)
    - Iran Aktuell, German publication for sympathizers of the Tudeh Party abroad, journal, 1983 February (Folder 1: 10)
    - Iraninform: A Marxist-Leninist Review (Rome: s.n.), journal, 1978 November (Folder 1: 11)
    - Kāvush, daftar-i t'urik-sīyāsī, sāl-i 1, shumārah-i 1, 5, and unknown, journals, 1356-1360 (1977-1981), undated (Folder 1: 12)
    - Mardum, urgān-i Hizb-i Tudah, newsletters, 1340-1369 (1961-1990) (Folder 1: 5-14)
      - Dawreh-yi 5, shumārah-i 23, 25, 28, 59, 69-70, 72-79, 81, 83-87, 91, 93-96, 1340 Mehr 10-1343 Day (1961 October-1964 December) (Folder 1: 5-8)
      - Dawreh-yi 6, shumārah-i 8, 11, 13, 16, 18-19, 24, 26, 28, 30, 35, 37-38, 40-47, 49, 60, 68, 74, 76, 80, 82 ,84 ,86, 89, 94, 96, 142, 145-146, 151 va 174, 1345 Esfand-1356 Tīr (1967 February-1977 June) (Folder 1: 9-11)
      - Sāl-i 1-2, shumārah-i 9-16, 1358 Āzar-1359 Tīr (1979 December-1980 June) (Folder 1: 12-13)
        Published after the revolution.
      - No. 333 (New Jersey: s.n.), 1990 October 16. (Folder 1: 14)
        English translation
    - Masā'il bayn'al-milālī (Stockholm: s.n.), journals, 1348-1367 (1969-1988) (Folder 1-3)
      Selected articles from the Review of the Communist and Worker Parties for Theory and Information.
      - 1348 va 1350 (1969 and 1971) (Folder 1: 15)
      - 1351-1352 (1972-1973) (Folder 2: 1-2)
      - 1353-1356 (1974-1977) (Folder 2: 3-5)
      - 1355-1357 (1976-1978) (Folder 2: 6)
      - 1359 (1980) (Folder 2: 7-8)
      - 1360 (1981) (Folder 2: 9)
      - 1360 (1981) (contd.) (Folder 3: 1)
      - 1361 (1982) (Folder 3: 2-3)
      - 1362-1363 (1983-1984) (Folder 3: 4)
      - 1367 (1988-1989) (Folder 3: 5)
    - Masā'il-i īrān va jahān, newspaper, 1361 Bahman (1983 February) (Folder 3: 6)
    - Navīd, sāl-i 3-4, shumārah-i 34, 38-39, 43-46, 54, 57-59, 71-72 (Stockholm: s.n.), newsletters, 1357 Tīr-Esfand (1978 July-1979 March) (Folder 3: 7)
    - Paykār, journals, 1350-1352 (1971-1973) (Folder 3-4:)
      - Sāl-i 1, shumārah-i 1-6, 1350 Khordād-1351 Ordibihisht (1971 June-1972 May) (Folder 3: 8-9)
      - Sāl-i 2, shumārah-i 1-3, 1351 Khordād-Mehr (1972 June-September) (Folder 3: 10)
      - Sāl-i 2 (contd.), shumārah-i 4-6, 1351 Ābān-1352 Ordibihisht (1972 October-1973 April) (Folder 4: 1)
      - Sāl-i 3, shumārah-i 1-6, 1352 Khordād-1353 Ordibihisht (1973 June-1974 April) (Folder 4: 2-4)
    - Payqām-i emruz, sāl-i 20, shumārah-i 14, 38, 40, newspapers, 1358 Esfand 2-Ordibihisht 4 (1979 March 17-April 24) (Folder 4: 5)
    - Payvand, neshri-yi mantaq-i junub, shumārah-i 2, journal, 1353 Esfand (1974 February) (Folder 4: 6)
    - Pazkvak, neshrī-yi khabarī bā kushash-i tudah-hā-yi mubārāz dar Berlin qarbī, shumārah-i 10-11, newsletter, 1366 Ordibihisht-Khordād (1987 May-June) (Folder 4: 7)
    - Porsish va pāsukh, Nur al-Dīn Kiyānurī (Tehran: Intishārat-i Hizb-i Tudah), journals, 1359-1361 (1980-1982) (Folder 4-5)
      Includes a series of titles relating to politics in Iran and the Tudeh Party. Arranged in numerical order by issue number.
      - "'Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān' va sīyāsat-i 'ittihād va mobārāzeh,'" shumārah-i 1, 1359 (1980) (Folder 4: 8)
      - "Porsish va pāsukh dar bāreh-yi mashī-yi sīyāsī Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān," shumārah-i 2, 1358 (1979) (Folder 4: 9)
      - "Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īran che-guneh mī negard?," shumārah-i 3, 1358 (1980) (Folder 4: 10)
      - "Mā va chap-i gariyān va masā'il-i inqilāb-i Īrān," shumārah-i 4, 1358 Day (1980 January) (Folder 4: 11)
      - "Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān che mī guyad?," shumārah-i 5, 1358 Bahman (1980 February) (Folder 5: 1)
      - "Movāzeh-yi mādar bāreh-yi shurāhā-yi masā'lih-yi Kordistān va jabhah motāhid-i khalq," shumārah-i 6, 1358 (1979) (Folder 5: 2)
      - "Masā'il-i dīruz va emrooz," shumārah-i 7, 1359 (1980) (Folder 5: 3)
      - "Tajāvuz-i impiriālīsm-i Amrīkā beh Jomhourī-yi Islāmī-yi Īrān bā shikast-i rubiru khvāhād ast," shumārah-i 8, 1359 (1980) (Folder 5: 4)
      - "Tavālat-i afqānistān va masā'il-i baqrenjī-i asr-i mā," shumārah-i 9, 1359 (1980) (Folder 5: 5)
      - "Vaz'i tabaqātī-yi jāmeh'yi Īrān va guru-hā-yi sīyāsī," shumārah-i 10, 1359 (1980) (Folder 5: 6)
      - "Zindigī-i pīsh'bīnī'hā-yi Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān rā ta'yid mi-kunad," shumārah-i 23, 1360 Khordād (1981 June) (Folder 5: 7)
      - Porsish va Pāsukh, general titles, 1360-1361 (1980-1982) (Folder 5: 8-9)
    - Rāh-i arānī, urgān-i markazī-i Hizb-i Dimukrātīk Mardum-i Īrān, newsletters, 1367-1368 (1988-1989) (Folder 5: 10-12)
      - Shumārah-i 1-6, 1367 Ordibihisht-Āzar (1988 May-December) (Folder 5: 10-11)
      - Shumārah-i 11, 15-16, 1368 Ordibihisht-Mehr (1989 May-October) (Folder 5: 12)
    - Rāh-i Tudah, newspapers, 1361-1363 (1982-1984) (Folder 5: 13-14)
      - Sāl-i 1, shumārah-i 9, 44-45, 47-51, 1361 Mehr-1362 Tīr (1982 October-1983 July) (Folder 5: 13)
      - Sāl-i 2, shumārah-i 53-56, 63, 80, 87, 91, 1362 Mordād-1363 Ordibihisht (1983 August-1984 May) (Folder 5: 14)
    - "Sālsālah-yi intishārat arānī" (S.l.: Hizb-i Tudah), journals, 1351-1352 (1972-1973) (Folder 6: 1)
    - Sitāreh-yi sorkh, urgān-i t'urik-sīyāsī sāzmān-i inqilābī, bound volume and journals, 1353-1358 (1974-1979) (Folder 6: 2-3)
      - Sāl-i 5-8, shumārah-i 40, 44, 46-63, 65, 68, 72-73, 75-81, 1353 Āzar-1357 Bahman (1974 December-1979 February) (Folder 6: 2)
      - Dawrah 3, shumārah-i 1-2, 1357 Esfand-1358 Mordād (1979 March-August) (Folder 6: 3)
    - Tudah, urgān-i sāzmān-i inqilābi-yi Hizb-i Tudah'i Īrān dar Khārij az Kishvar, newspaper and journals, 1345-1352 (1966-1973) (Folder 6: 4-7)
      - Shumārah-i 3-4, newspapers, 1345 Tīr-Mordād (1966 July-August) (Folder 6: 4)
      - Shumārah-i 13 va 15, 19-21, journals, 1348 Khordād-1350 Mordād (1969 June-1971 August) (Folder 6: 5-6)
      - Shumārah-i 21, 1352 Āzar/Day (1973 December/January) (Folder 6: 7)
        Not related to issue number 21 in Box 6, Folder 6
    - Tudeh News, International Bulletin of the Tudeh Party of Iran, nos. 103, 114, 121-122, 124, 126-128, 132-133, 140-142, 147-148, 157-158, newsletters, 1988 December-1993 February (Folder 6: 8)
    - Vazheh nāmeh: vizheh-yi barnāmeh-yi Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān, (S.l.: Intishārat-i Hizb-i Tudah), journal, 1365 (1986) (Folder 6: 9)
  - Monographs, booklets, and pamphlets (Folder 6-12)
    - 2 enteqād beh Chirīk'hā-yi Fadā'ī-i Khalq, Mustafā Shu'ā'īyān (Florence: Mazdak), monograph, 1355 (1976) (Folder 6: 10)
    - 5 nāmeh-yi sar goshādeh beh sāzmān-i chirīk'hā-yi fadā'ī-i khalq-i īrān, Mustafā Shu'ā'īyān (Florence: Mazdak), monograph, circa 1359 (1980) (Folder 6: 11)
    - 18 sāl pushtibānī az khat-i imām: Hizb-i Tudah va Junbish-i Khunīn 15 Khordād, (S.l.: s.n.), booklet, 1360 (1981) (Folder 6: 12)
    - Afsāneh-yi 'khalq-hā-yi' īrān, M. Makan (Florence: Mazdak), booklet, 1348 Tabistān (1969) (Folder 6: 13)
    - Afsāneh-yi talā'hā-yi īrān, F.M. Javānshir (S.l.: Intisharat-i Hizb-i Tudah-'i Irān), booklet, 1358 (1979) (Folder 6: 14)
    - Alifbā-yi mubārāzāh, (S.l.: Hizb-i Tudah), chāp-i 2 va chāp-i 3, booklets, 134? va 1356 (196? and 1977) (Folder 6: 15)
    - Artish-i 'azīm-i zanān beh maidan mīyaid, M. Mohammadi, booklet, undated (Folder 7: 1)
    - Asar va maqālat, Dr. Taqi Arāni (Tehran: Arān Taqui), monograph, 1357 (1978) (Folder 7: 2)
    - Asarī az Khosrow Golesorkhī (Selected Writings and Poetry) (Florence: Mazdak), monograph, 1353 (1974) (Folder 7: 3)
    - Asnād va dīdgāh-hā, pulunum 1 va 2 va 3 va pulunum-i chāhārum (vasiā) kumiteh-yi markazī-yi Hizb-i Tudah, (Los Angeles: Hizb-i Tudah), booklet, undated (Folder 7: 4)
    - Asnād-i kunfirāns-i tadarokātī-yi sartāsari junbish-i Tudah-hā-yi mobāriz infisali, (France: Rivero), monograph, 1366 (1987) (Folder 7: 5)
    - Avetis Sultanzade: The Forgotten Revolutionary Theoretician (Life and Works), Cosroe Chaqueri, (Tehran: Antidote), booklet, circa 1985 (Folder 7: 6)
    - "Bar nāmeh-yi Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān," pamphlets, 1354-1360 (1975-1981), undated (Folder 7: 7)
    - Barāh-yi mutavqif sākhtan-i tirur va sarkubdar 'arāq, (Tehran: Hizb-i Tudah), booklet, 1358 Ābān (1979 October) (Folder 7: 8)
    - Barkhī masā'il-i had-i inqilāb-i īrān: majmu'āh-'i maqālat, Ihsān Tabarī, monograph, 1358 (1979) (Folder 7: 9)
    - Barrasī-yi mukhtasar ahzāb-i burzhvāzī-yi millī-'i īrān dar muqābilah bā junbish-i kārgarī va inqilābī-yi īrān, Rasul Mihrabān (Los Angeles: Payk-i Īrān), monograph, 1359 (1980), undated (Folder 7: 10-11)
    - Barrasī va rīshahyabi-yi astabahat-i Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īran dar chihārsāl-i avvalī-yi inqilāb, Rasul Mihrabān (S.l: Payk-i Irān), monograph, 1365 Khordād (1986 May) (Folder 7: 12)
    - Baz hām muftarīyān, (S.l: Intishārat-i Hizb-i Tudah), monograph, 1365 (1986) (Folder 7: 13)
    - Bipā khīz īrān-i man!, (S.l: Intishārat-i Arānī), booklet, 1355 (1976) (Folder 7: 14)
    - Bīyānī-yi entikhābatī-yi kumiteh markazī-yi Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān, Hizb-i Tudah dar Frankfurt, pamphlet, 1358 Day (1979) (Folder 7: 15)
    - Chand nivishteh, Mustafā Shu'ā'īyān (Florence: Mazdak), monograph, 1355 (1976) (Folder 8: 1)
    - Chand shi'r az pahnah-yi nabard, Mustafā Shu'ā'īyān (Florence: Mazdak), monograph, circa 1356 (1977) (Folder 8: 2)
    - Chāvushan-i nuzā'i-i kabīr: beh munasbit-i 42 sāl-i kār-i hamāsah-'i hizb-i tudah-'i īrān, (United States: Sāzmān-i Havādārān-i Hizb), monograph, 1362 (1983) (Folder 8: 3)
      Book of poetry
    - Cherā impiriālīsm va irtejā' az Hizb-i Tudah-'i Ī rān vahasht dārand?, (S.l: Intishārat-i Hizb-i Tudah), monograph, 1363 (1984) (Folder 8: 4)
    - Chihil sāl-i nabard-i bi'vagfahdar rāh-i ittihād-i nīruhā-yi zidd-i impiriālīstī va mardumī, (West Germany: Intishārāt-i Sāzmān-i Hizb-i Tudah dar Allemān Federal), booklet, 1360 (1981) (Folder 8: 5)
    - Chirīk'hā-yi fadā'ī-i chi mī guyand?, F.M. Javānshir (Stassfurt: Tudeh Publishing Centre), monograph, 1351 (1972) (Folder 8: 6)
    - Dar bāreh-yi bahzī az masā'il-i, Amir Yavari, (Paris: Intishārat-i Hizb-i Tudah), monograph, 1969 March (Folder 8: 7)
    - Dar bāreh-yi junbish-i āzādi baksh-i millī, V.I. Lenin (Florence: Mazdak), booklet, circa 1352 (1973) (Folder 8: 8)
    - Dar bāreh-yi mantaq-i 'amal, Ihsān Tabari (S.l: Sāzmān-i Javānān Tudah-'i Irān), monograph, 1360 Azar (1981 December) (Folder 8: 9)
    - Dar bāreh-yi Mārks, Ingels, va Mārksīsm, V.I. Lenin (Florence: Mazdak), booklet, 1349 (1970) (Folder 8: 10)
    - Dar bāreh-yi mas'ālih-yi Stālīn: majmuah'i az nazārat, (Florence: Intishārat-i Mazdak), booklet, 1350s (1970s) (Folder 8: 11)
    - Dar bāreh-yi mubārzāt-i Kurdistān, Hamid Mu'mini (S.l: Intishārat-i Shabāhangi), booklet, 1358 (1979) (Folder 8: 12)
    - Dar bāreh-yi mutaliāh va 'aliāh kitāb parastī, Mao Tse Tung (Florence?: Mazdak), booklet, circa 1350s (1970s) (Folder 8: 13)
    - Dars-hā-i az Shīlī, Louis Corvalan and Edward Burstein (S.l: Intishārat-i Hizb-i Tudah), monograph, undated (Folder 8: 14)
    - Daw maqālah dar bāreh-yi tabliqat, Ihsān Tabari and Mehrdād Puyā (S.l.: Intishārat-i Hizb-i Tudah), booklet, 1361 Ābān (1982 October) (Folder 8: 15)
    - Didar bā ārash, Haidār Mihrgān (Tehran: 16 Azar), booklets, 1360 (1981) (Folder 8: 16)
    - Estālīnīsm va bolshuvīzm, Leon Trotsky (S.l.: Intishārat Tali'eh), monograph, 1354 Tir (1975 July) (Folder 8: 17)
    - Ettā'at-i kur kurāneh Khusraw Ruzbih, (Arlington, Va.: Asia Books and Periodicals), monograph, 1357 (1978) (Folder 9: 1)
    - Faslī dar golesorkh, Atifāh Gorgin (editor) (Paris: A. Gorgin), journal, 1365 (1986) (Folder 9: 2)
    - Furu' pashī-i hizam sunatī va zayish-i sarmāyah' darī dar īrān, Ihsān Tabari (S.l: Hizb-i Tudah), monograph, 1354 (1975) (Folder 9: 3)
    - Guftegu'ī bā Chirīk'hā-yi Fadā'ī-i Khalq-i Īrān dar bāreh-yi masā'il-i inqilāb-i īrān, (S.l: Intishārat-i Hizb), booklet, 1358 Khordād (1979 June) (Folder 9: 4)
    - Guzārish-i haiat-i sīyāsī beh hifdahumin pulunum (vasi) Kumiteh Markazī-i Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān, (S.l.: s.n.), booklets, 1360 (1981) (Folder 9: 5)
    - Hamāsah-'i 23 Tīr: gushah'i az mobārzāt-i kārgarān-i naft-i Khuzīstān, F.M. Javānshir (S.l: Intishārat-i Hizb-i Tudah), monograph, 1359 (1980) (Folder 9: 6)
    - Hekām-i tārīkh beh pīsh mī ravad, Nur-al Din Kiyānuri, pamphlets, 1361 Shahrivar (1982 September) (Folder 9: 7)
    - Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān az khatt-i imām pushtibānī mī kunad, (S.l: Hizb-i Tudah), booklet, 1358 (1979) (Folder 9: 8)
    - Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īran va Doktor Mohammad Mosaddeq, Nur al-Din Kiyānurī (S.l.: s.n.), chāp-i 2, monographs, 1359 Khordād-Farvardīn (1980 April) (Folder 9: 9)
    - Inqilāb-i prulitāryā'i va farhang, N. Bukharin (S.l.: Intishārat-i Kumunīsm), monograph, 1357 (1978) (Folder 9: 10)
    - Inqilāb-i Uktubir va Īrān, (S.l.: Intishārat-i Shabhih Tablīqāt-i Hizb-i Tudah-'i Irān), monograph, 1346 (1967) (Folder 9: 11)
    - Iran, three essays on: Imperialism, the Revolutionary Left, and the Guerrilla Movement, A.P. Pouyan and M. Mani (Florence: Edition Mazdak), monograph, circa 1973 (Folder 9: 12)
    - Jahān-i sivvum va daw abar ghudrat, (Rome: Intishārat-i Sāzmān-i Hizb), booklet, 1353 (1974) (Folder 9: 13)
    - Jang sāzish va yik nāmeh va yik shi'r, Mustafā Shu'ā'īyān (Florence: Intishārat-i Mazdak), monograph, 1355 (1977) (Folder 9: 14)
    - Javidān-i bad khātireh-yi qiām-i khunīn tabrīz, dar bāreh-yi mobārzāt Tudah-hā, (S.l.: Intishārat-i Sāzmān-i Inqilābī), booklet, 1356 Zimistān (1977) (Folder 9: 15)
    - Junbish-i rahā'i baksh-i Turkmanhā-yi Īrān (Qiām sāl-hā-yi 1917-1925), K. Atayif (West New York, N.J.: Mardum), monograph, 1366 (1987) (Folder 10: 1)
    - Kurd-hā chi mī guyand?, Abdullah Ghadir, monograph, 1364 Khordād (1985 June) (Folder 10: 2)
    - Linin va khurdih burjvāz-hā, M. Gorky (Florence: Mazdak), monograph, 1346 (1967) (Folder 10: 3)
    - Mā va dīdgāh'hā-yi naw dar junbish-i chap-i īrān, Heidār Mihrgān (Calif.: Hizb-i Tudah), booklet, 1358 Āzar (1979) (Folder 10: 4)
    - Mā va musalmanān-i mubārāz, publication of the Organization of Democratic Youth and Students in Iran (ODYSI), booklet, undated (Folder 10: 5)
    - Mā va vāzadigān-i sīyāsī, (S.l.: Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān), booklet, 1366 (1987) (Folder 10: 6)
    - Māhiat-i tabaqātī-yi dulat-i shurāvī: dulat-i kārgarī va masālah-i tirmidur va Bunāpārtīsm, Leon Trotsky (S.l.: s.n.), monograph, 1354 Mordād (1975 August) (Folder 10: 7)
    - Mārksīst-hā va masālih zanān, (Florence: Mazdak), booklet, 1354 (1975) (Folder 10: 8)
    - Masā'lih-yi dīhqāni dar farānseh va āllemān va millī kardan-i zamīn, (Florence: Mazdak), booklet, 1354 (1975) (Folder 10: 9)
    - Matirīālīsm dīālīktīkī, Taqi Arāni (Florence: Mazdak), booklet, undated (Folder 10: 10)
    - Matn-i ākharīn difā'-i rafīq shahīd Khusraw Ruzbih, (Stassfurt: Hizb-i Tudah), chāp-i 3, booklet, 1349 (1970) (Folder 10: 11)
    - Ma'u'īsm va bāztāb-i ān dar īrān, F.M. Javānshir (Stassfurt: Hizb-i Tudah), monograph, 1353 (1974) (Folder 10: 12)
    - Mobārzāt-i tabaqāti dar Farānseh, Karl Marx (Intishārat-i Kārgar), booklet, 1356 (1977) (Folder 10: 13)
    - Muntakhābī az āsar-i: Hu-Shī-Min, (Florence: Mazdak), booklets, circa 1350s (1970s) (Folder 10: 14)
    - Muqādim-i iqtisād-i sīyāsī, (Florence: Bungāh-i Intishārat-i Mazdak), booklet, 1348 Pāiz (1969) (Folder 10: 15)
    - Muqādamiah-yi iqtisād-i sīyāsī va Mārksīsm, Lenin and Lange (Florence: Mazdak), monograph, 1355 (1976) (Folder 10: 16)
    - Nāmeh-hā az zindān, Jafar Vakili, (Tehran: Intishārat-i 'Aram), chāp-2, monograph, undated (Folder 10: 17)
    - "Nāmeh beh rufuqā," pamphlet, 1363 Pāiz (1984) (Folder 10: 18)
    - Nāmeh-yi sargoshādeh beh Kumiteh-yi Markazī Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān, Iraj Iskandari, booklet, 1364 Day (1985 December) (Folder 10: 19)